A Guide to the Papers of Collins Denny 1872-1943
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Collins Denny 1872-1943
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2672
This collection consists of 30,000 items.
Gary L. Cardwell and Phillip Rosen
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The first portion of the Denny papers was received by the Library in 1947 as a gift from Collins Denny, Jr., and several additions were made by Mr. Denny before his death. The largest and most important group (#2672-c) included some 6,000 items received in 1951. In 1969, Mr. Denny's sons, Collins Denny III and Clifford M. Denny, presented all the remaining files of their grandfather which could be located in the storage areas of the family farm near Richmond.
Biographical/Historical Information
Chronology
1854 May 28 Born in Winchester, Va., son of William Ritenour and Margaret Ann (Collins) Denny. Collins' grandparents were William and Margaret (Hotsenpeller) Denny, descendants of David and Margaret (?) Denny, who emigrated from Londonderry, Ireland about 1720 and settled in Frederick County, Va. William R. Denny, his father was a manufacturer, President of the Winchester and Potomac Railroad, and a former Lt. Col. in the Confederate Army during the Civil War.
[1872?] After a preparatory education at Shenandoah Valley Academy in Winchester, Va., Collins Denny attended the College of New Jersey (later, Princeton University) where he was active in debating and captain of the 1875 football team. His major interests appear to have been courses in history, philosophy, ethics, and English literature (see notes: also Physics and Mathematics). He also participated in gymnastics.
1876 June 28 Graduated from the College of New Jersey with an A.B. His oration, "Failure an Element of Success," was a part of the program.
1876-1877 Studied law at the University of Virginia Law School, receiving his L.L.B. in 1877.
1877 Admitted to the Maryland Bar
1877-1879 Practiced Law in Baltimore, Md., specializing in real estate, banking and patent matters.
1879 Received an A.M. from the College of New Jersey. Left law practice to enter the ministry of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South, Baltimore Conference. Served nine years under Bishop A. W. Wilson as a circuit and station preacher in that conference (1880-89).
1886 Appointed by the College of Bishops to accompany Bishop A. W. Wilson on a tour of visitation to missions in Asia, at which time he made a tour around the World. (He later would twice spend months in Europe).
1889-1891 Served as chaplain at the University of Virginia. He also took post graduate work in Anglo-Saxon, Philosophy, the English language and literature.
1891 Appointed Professor of Moral Philosophy at Vanderbilt University, Nashville, Tennessee, and served 19 years.
1894 Appointed to the Book Committee of the M.E. Church, S. and served as editor, etc. of the Nashville, Tennessee, branch of the Methodist Publishing House.
1898-1910 Appointed as Chairman of the Book Committee by the College of Bishops, and served 12 years
1902 June Received membership in Phi Beta Kappa
1908 Received an honorary degree (D.D.) at Washington and Lee University
1910 Received L.L.D. degrees at Emory & Henry College and Emory University
1910 Elected Bishop of the M.E. Church, S. with residence at Richmond, Va.
1910-1927 Served as Secretary to the church's college of Bishops
1915 Appointed to go to Mexico to investigate and oversee church affairs
1917-1919 Served as member of the Virginia state council of defense and the Virginia History Commission
1939 Denny doubted the legality and disapproved of the final Plan of Unification which resulted in the merger of the Methodist Episcopal Church and the M.E. Church, South. Until his death he considered himself a bishop at the latter denomination only
1943 May 12 Died in Richmond, Virginia
Genealogical Information
Linna, Irene and Fanny (Fitch) are daughters of Alexander Denny (William R.'s half-brother). They were half-nieces. Agnes Barton Collins is Benson Collins' wife. Susanna, their daughter. "Belle" Denny is John Henry Denny's wife (Collins Sr.'s sister-in-law). Roscoe White is Edith Allen (Denny) White's husband. Denny, Lou, and Marvin their children. Melancthon ("Doc") James is Margaret (or Peggy) Denny James' husband. Donald, Marguerite and Helen their children. Harvey Campbell is Mary Brown (Denny) Campbell's husband. James W. Denny is a half-cousin of Collins, Sr. The same applies to Denny Bros. in San Marcos, Texas. James W. was the son of Robert Lewis Denny, the sixth child of William of Stevensburg by his first wife. William R. Denny (12th child) was a child by the second wife. The Chapman Family is not included in this family tree but is isolated in the correspondence. Lillie Chapman is Lucy Chapman Denny's sister; W.C. Lowndes is her husband; Andrew and W.C., Jr. their children. William Chapman is Lucy Denny's cousin.
Scope and Content Information
This collection, filling about eighty-eight Hollinger storage boxes comprises the papers of Collins Denny, prominent Southern Methodist Bishop, teacher, author, and lawyer. The collection contains a very complete file of Denny's incoming correspondence, together with some carbons of the outgoing correspondence, (there are gaps in this file), both personal and official, as well as newspaper clippings about his career, drafts of his books, speeches, sermons, and articles, memorablilia, and materials and correspondence of the Collins and Denny families.
The collection is rich in letters from Bishop Warren A. Candler; from Bishop James Canon, Jr., the "Dry Messiah"; and from Noah K. Davis, about whose writings Denny wrote his most prestigious work, an analysis of Davis' Elements of Deductive Logic and his Elements of Psychology. The collection will also provide an excellent basis for studies of any of the following topics: the organization and governance of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South; the protracted struggle over the unification of the Methodist Episcopal Chruch, and the Methodist Episcopal Church, South; the bitter court and church struggle over the trusteeship of Vanderbuilt University; and the Congressional controversy over the conduct of the Book Agents of the Publishing House of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South. As indicated by these suggested topics, the collection seems to hold the most for the historian particularly interested in the first quarter of this century.
Organization
The general arrangement of the Collins Denny, and Denny and Collins Family Papers, is in ten major series, as follows:
Series I: Collins Denny Correspondence: Boxes 1-60. Denny's own filing system has been preserved intact for the most part. Incoming and outgoing letters are segregated and filed alphabetically, within a chronological framework. This last consists of five sub-series as follows:
Sub-Series One: 1872-1899, Boxes 1-17
Sub-Series Two: 1900-1910, Boxes 8-19
Sub-Series Three: 1911-1922, Boxes 20-43
Sub-Series Four: 1923-1943, Boxes 44-52
Sub-Series Five: By states, Boxes 53-60.
Within Denny's own correspondence, subseries Five is an exception. Letters here are filed according to states. The correspondence is designated "official" because Denny was acting as Secretary of the College of Bishops.
Within each of the chronological series there are isolated correspondents. These major correspondents are filed within the alphabeticall order but prior to the alphabetical folder itself. The general arrangement of each chronological series is: (for ex.) A. W. Wilson, Woodrow Wilson, Wi's (incoming), Wi's (outgoing).
All the letters of each of the isolated correspondents are placed in one folder or a group of folder in only one place in the papers. Thus there is only one folder of Woodrow Wilson's incoming correspondence. Similarly, all of Bishop W. A. Chandler's correspondence to Denny is in Series One (Boxes 1 & 2) despite the fact that seven of the eight such folders lie outside the series chronologically. The place of any group of letters has been determined, chronologically, by the first letter in the collection. Denny's outgoing letters to each individual must be sought in the alphabetically arranged outgoing files in series.
Series II: Family correspondence, Boxes 61-65.
Series III: Collins Denny: Speeches, articles, and other writings, Boxes 66-70, chronologically arranged.
Series IV: Collins Denny: Sermons and Sermon notes, Box 71.
Series V: Collins Denny: Personal documents, certificates, and items useful for biographical purposes, Box 72.
Series VI: Collins Denny: Notes--academic and on church history, Boxes 73-75.
Series VII: Collins Denny and church matters: Clippings, Boxes 76-80.
Series VIII: Collins Denny: Memorabilia, Box 81, arranged chronologically.
Series IX: Collins Denny Collection: Boxes 82-85, subdivided topically into Methodist Collection; Civil War and Reconstruction; and Miscellaneous, arranged chronologically.
Series X: Denny and Collins Family Papers: Boxes 86-87. Miscellaneous: Box 88.
Index of Major Correspondents
Ainsworth, Bishop William N. (Box 8 folder 1)
Alderman, Edwin A. (Box 8 folder 2)
Aktins, Bishop James (Box 8 folder 10)
Beauchamp, Bishop W. B. (Box 8 folder 17)
Candler, Bishop W. A. (Box 1 folder 16-20; Box 2 folder 1-3)
Cannon, Bishop James, Jr. (Box 2 folder 4)
Cranston, Bishop Earl (Box 24 folder 3)
Daniels, Josephus (Box 24 folder 15)
Darlington, Bishop U. V. W. (Box 24 folder 16-17)
Davis, Noah K. (Box 2 folder 13-15)
Decell, Bishop J. Lloyd (Box 44 folder 12)
Dickey, James E. (Box 10 folder 2)
Dobbs, Bishop Hoyt M. (Box 10 folder 3)
Dubose, Bishop H. M. (Box 10 folder 4)
Freeman, Douglas Southall (Box 26 folder 2)
Galloway, Bishop Charles B. (Box 3 folder 9)
Hamilton, Bishop John W. (Box 27 folder 7)
Hartzell, Bishop Joseph C. (Box 27 folder 17)
Hay, Bishop Samuel R. (Box 12 folder 2)
Hendrix, Bishop E. R. (Box 3 folder 17)
Hoss, Bishop E. E. (Box 4 folder 1-3)
Hughes, Bishop Edwin H. (Box 47 folder 2)
Jones, Bob (Box 30 folder 5)
Kern, Bishop Paul (Box 12 folder 15)
Kilgo, Bishop John (Box 12 folder 17)
Kirkland, J. H. (Box 4 folder 19)
Lambuth, Bishop W. R. (Box 4 folder 22)
Leete, Bishop folder D. (Box 48 folder 12)
McDowell, Bishop W. F. (Box 14 folder 1)
McMurry, Bishop W. F. (Box 14 folder 5)
Murrah, Bishop W. B. (Box 14 folder 4)
Moore, Bishop Arthur (Box 49 folder 18)
Moore, Bishop John M. (Box 5 folder 8)
Mouzon, Bishop E. D. (Box 34 folder 1-2)
Page, Thomas Nelson (Box 15 folder 15)
Purcell, Bishop Clare (Box 36 folder 7)
Smith Bishop A. Coke (Box 6 folder 6-7)
Waterhouse, Bishop R. G. (Box 18 folder 23)
Williams, John Sharp (Box 19 folder 4)
Wilson, Bishop A. W. (Box 7 folder 10-11)
Wilson, Woodrow (Box 19 folder 5)
Contents List
- Collins Denny Correspondence
  - 1872-1899
    - Gross Alexander to Collins Denny 1897 August 3-1914 July 6 (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Jno. I Armstrong to Collins Denny 1899 April 30-1905 January 28 (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Collins Denny Sr. Outgoing Correspondence: A's n.d. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - J.D. Barbee to Collins Denny 1892 July 29-1920 June 3 (Box-folder 1:4)
    - W. M. Baskerville to Collins Denny 1891 June 18-1897 August 27 (Box-folder 1:5)
    - W. H. Bates to Collins Denny 1897 March 9-1901 February 14 (Box-folder 1:6)
    - Board of Church Extention to Collins Denny 1911 March 24-1912 March 30 (Box-folder 1:7)
    - M. F. Bragg to Collins Denny 1898 April 19-1914 November 24 (Box-folder 1:8)
    - William C. Branham to Collins Denny 1897 September 23-1897 November 18 (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Mrs. E. G. Buford to Collins Denny 1892 November 12-1901 May 13 (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Charles Bulla to Collins Denny 1898 July 9-1921 September 2 (Box-folder 1:11)
    - David Bush to Collins Denny 1898 November 15-1921 May 24 (Box-folder 1:12)
    - Nicholas M. Butler to Collins Denny 1894 January 8-1894 February 26 (Box 1:13)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence 1890; B's (Box-folder 1:14)
    - Collins Denny Sr. Outgoing Correspondence: B's 1898 (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Bishop W. A. Candler to Collins Denny 1897 April 23-1910 October 8 (Box-folder 1:16)
    - Bishop W. A. Candler to Collins Denny 1911 January 28-1915 November 20 (Box-folder 1:17)
    - W. A. Candler to Collins Denny 1916 March 3-1918 December 9 (Box-folder 1:18)
    - W. A. Candler to Collins Denny 1919 January 13-1922 December 27 (Box-folder 1:19)
    - W. A. Candler to Collins Denny 1923 January 6-1924 August 29 (Box-folder 1:20)
    - W. A. Candler to Collins Denny 1925 January 1-1927 November 28 (Box-folder 2:1)
    - W. A. Candler to Collins Denny 1928 January 10-1932 December 31 (Box-folder 2:2)
    - W. A. Candler to Collins Denny 1933 February 17-1938 January 18 (Box-folder 2:3)
    - Bishop James Cannon to Collins Denny 1907 April 18-1937 September 21 (Box-folder 2:4)
    - James Charmer to Collins Denny 1890 May 19-1898 March 22 (Box-folder 2:5)
    - F. H. Chalmers to Collins Denny 1894 March 30-1897 July 23 (Box-folder 2:6)
    - Joe Cook to Collins Denny 1896 October 19-1897 May 17 (Box-folder 2:7)
    - T. W. Crowder to Collins Denny 1895 December 31-1898 June 5 (Box-folder 2:8)
    - T. L. Cuyler to Collins Denny 1890 December 13-1891 March 24 (Box-folder 2:9)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence; C's 1872-1899 (Box-folder 2:10)
    - Collins Denny Sr. Correspondence--Outgoing n.d. (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence 1876-1899 (Box-folder 2:12)
      re: Church trial of Andrew Jackson Davis (Salem, Va.), 1887
    - Noah K. Davis to Collins Denny 1890 June 12-1895 November 21 (Box-folder 2:13)
    - Noah K. Davis to Collins Denny 1896 March 25-1903 December 15 (Box-folder 2:14)
    - Noah K. Davis to Collins Denny 1904 January 28-1909 December 23 (Box-folder 2:15)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence 1897 February. 19-1900 January 25 (Box-folder 2:16)
      re: Denny Bros.(San Marco, Texas)
    - W. C. Dibrell to Collins Denny 1899 November 11-1920 December 23 (Box-folder 2:17)
    - E. E. Dinwiddie to Collins Denny 1891 February 17-1897 March 18 (Box-folder 2:18)
    - E. J. Drinkhouse to Collins Denny 1898 September 15-1898 November 21 (Box-folder 2:19)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence 1889 September 19 (Box-folder 2:20)
      re: Church trial of Harry W. Druit
    - Collins Denny Correspondence; D's n.d. (Box 3:1)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence--Outgoing n.d. (Box-folder 3:2)
    - W. C. Everett to Collins Denny 1899 November 7-1921 June 16 (Box-folder 3:3)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence and Briefs 1872-1899 (Box-folder 3:4)
      re: Faurot vs. Winchester Paper Co. Case
    - T. T. Fishburne to Collins Denny 1891 November 25-1917 December 15 (Box-folder 3:5)
    - G. C. Fraser to Collins Denny 1893 May 2-1892 December 12 (Box-folder 3:6)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence 1872-1899 (Box-folder 3:7)
    - Collins Denny Sr. Correspondence n.d. (Box-folder 3:8)
    - Charles Galloway to Collins Denny 1899 May 31-1905 March 2 (Box-folder 3:9)
    - J. E. Gilbert to Collins Denny 1895 March 12-1896 January 28 (Box-folder 3:10)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence: G's n.d. (Box 3:11)
    - J. D. Hamilton to Collins Denny 1891 September 14-1919 March 7 (Box-folder 3:12)
    - H. L. Harrison to Collins Denny 1891 January 10-1898 October 10 (Box-folder 3:13)
    - W. F. Hammer to Collins Denny 1891 June 30-1898 February 15 (Box-folder 3:14)
    - Harper & Brothers to Collins Denny 1892 September 12-1896 August 21 (Box-folder 3:15)
    - J. A. Handley to Collins Denny 1895 November 7-1897 May 31 (Box-folder 3:16)
    - Bishop E. R. Hendrix to Collins Denny 1891 January 27-1921 December 6 (Box-folder 3:17)
    - Henry Holt & Co. to Collins Denny 1892 December 19-1892 February 17 (Box-folder 3:18)
    - Bishop E. E. Hoss to Collins Denny 1892 July 28-1919 February 2 (Box-folder 4:1)
    - Bishop E. E. Hoss to Collins Denny 1914 February 7-1919 February 2 (Box-folder 4:2)
    - E. E. Hoss, Jr. to Collins Denny 1923 December 3-1925 July 24 (Box-folder 4:3)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence 1900-1910 (Box-folder 4:4)
      Letters re: Honorary Degrees, 1892, 1909 & 1910
    - German H. Hunt to Collins Denny 1898 May 11-1898 July 14 (Box-folder 4:5)
    - J. S. Hutchinson to Collins Denny 1889 December 24-1899 April (Box-folder 4:6)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence; H's 1872-1899 (Box-folder 4:7)
    - Collins Denny Sr. Correspondence--Outgoing n.d. (Box-folder 4:8)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence n.d. (Box-folder 4:9)
      re: Letters of Introduction
    - Illinois Central Railroad to Collins Denny 1898 January 14-1898 April 27 (Box-folder 4:10)
    - Richard Irby to Collins Denny 1897 October 26-1902 April 21 (Box-folder 4:11)
    - Correspondence to Collins Denny n.d. (Box-folder 4:12)
    - J.C. Jones to Collins Denny 1897 March 12-1898 February 8 (Box-folder 4:13)
    - Thomas M. Jones to Collins Denny 1891 September 16-1897 December 11 (Box-folder 4:14)
    - Wm. Jones to Collins Denny 1896 February 17-1904 May 28 (Box-folder 4:15)
    - Correspondence to Collins Denny; J's n.d. (Box-folder 4:16)
    - Collins Denny Sr. Correspondence; J's n.d. (Box-folder 4:17)
    - J. A. Kern to Collins Denny 1893 March 8-1899 September 7 (Box-folder 4:18)
    - J. H. Kirkland to Collins Denny 1894 May 7-1909 November 1 (Box-folder 4:19)
    - W. D. Kirkland to Collins Denny 1894 June 6-1895 May 13 (Box-folder 4:20)
    - D.C. Kelly to Collins Denny 1893 December 1-1898 June 20 (Box-folder 4:21)
    - Bishop Walter B. Lambuth to Collins Denny 1890 September 11-1921 March 23 (Box-folder 4:22)
    - John J. Laferty to Collins Denny 1898 September 8- n.d. (Box-folder 4:23)
    - James W. Lee to Collins Denny 1895 December 24-1917 July 5 (Box-folder 4:24)
    - W.C. Lovett to Collins Denny 1895 March 19-1920 March 8 (Box-folder 4:25)
    - M.E. Lynham to Collins Denny 1891 September 16-1892 December 22 (Box-folder 4:26)
    - Correspondence to Collins Denny; L's n.d. (Box-folder 4:27)
    - Robert Magruder to Collins Denny 1896 June 6-1898 April 23 (Box-folder 5:1)
    - Charles Marshall to Collins Denny 1897 September 24-1902 April 2 (Box-folder 5:2)
    - J. M. Mason to Collins Denny 1897 November 9-1900 February 5 (Box-folder 5:3)
    - Correspondence & Materials n.d. (Box-folder 5:4)
      re: McKelden vs. Hildt
    - Page Milburn to Collins Denny 1890 March 25-1910 May 18 (Box-folder 5:5)
    - John B. Minor to Collins Denny 1879 December 19-1887 July 4 (Box-folder 5:6)
    - W. F. Moncreiff to Collins Denny 1892 August 3-1903 February 2 (Box-folder 5:7)
    - Bishop John M. Moore to Collins Denny 1893 October 21-1937 September 16 (Box-folder 5:8)
    - Jos. B. Morgan to Collins Denny 1894 July 7-1916 August 12 (Box-folder 5:9)
    - Jos. B. Morgan to Collins Denny 1917 January 6-1928 January 11 (Box-folder 5:10)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence; M's n.d. (Box-folder 5:11)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence--Outgoing; M's n.d. (Box-folder 5:12)
    - T. W. Neaden to Collins Denny 1891 November 26-1898 January 3 (Box-folder 5:13)
    - W. L. Nelms to Collins Denny 1896 May 6-1910 May 4 (Box-folder 5:14)
    - Paul K. Nugart to Collins Denny 1896 June 30-1904 March 1 (Box-folder 5:15)
    - O. D. Oakey to Collins Denny 1897 August 14-1920 July 28 (Box-folder 5:16)
    - A. R. Pendleton to Collins Denny 1878 March 18-1879 February 26 (Box-folder 5:17)
      also copy of legal brief--Pendleton vs. State of Maryland and City of Baltimore
    - R. H. Peoples to Collins Denny 1899 October 23-1910 May 25 (Box-folder 5:18)
    - J. R. Pepper to Collins Denny 1892 July 18-1927 November 15 (Box-folder 5:19)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence 1876 (Box-folder 5:20)
      re: Letters of Recommendation from Princeton
    - Collins Denny Correspondence; P's n.d. (Box-folder 5:21)
    - Collins Denny Sr. Correspondence--Outgoing; P's n.d. (Box-folder 5:22)
    - John J. Ranson to Collins Denny 1899 June 30-1919 January 27 (Box-folder 5:23)
    - H. B. Reams to Collins Denny 1892 June 28-1938 May 21 (Box-folder 5:24)
    - E. C. Reeves to Collins Denny 1898 June 16-1928 September 14 (Box-folder 5:25)
    - W. H. Robert to Collins Denny 1895 October. 14-1895 December 31 (Box-folder 5:26)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence; R's 1872-1899 (Box-folder 5:27)
    - George Savage to Collins Denny 1895 November 8-1897 January 1 (Box-folder 6:1)
    - Chas. Scribner's Sons to Collins Denny 1899 January 21-1905 September 15 (Box-folder 6:2)
    - Sheldon & Co. to Collins Denny 1890 February 20-1893 March 9 (Box-folder 6:3)
    - W. H. Shuff to Collins Denny 1891 September 30-1897 July 30 (Box-folder 6:4)
    - Sam W. Small to Collins Denny 1888 February 17- 1888 (Box-folder 6:5)
    - Bishop A. Coke Smith to Collins Denny 1892 June 24-1899 December 29 (Box-folder 6:6)
    - Bishop A. Coke Smith to Collins Denny 1900 February 23-1906 September 25 (Box-folder 6:7)
    - D. M. Smith to Collins Denny 1896 June 19-1921 October 6 (Box-folder 6:8)
    - Kitty Coke Smith to Collins Denny 1901 June 6-1917 October 11 (Box-folder 6:9)
    - Kate K. Smith to Collins Denny 1894 September 7-1911 January 9 (Box-folder 6:10)
    - Robert Smith to Collins Denny 1889 November 12-1895 January 14 (Box-folder 6:11)
    - E. B. Stahlman to Collins Denny 1895 March 19-1905 October 16 (Box-folder 6:12)
    - Chas. S. Stanton to Collins Denny 1895 January 28-1912 March 16 (Box-folder 6:13)
    - S. A. Steel to Collins Denny 1891 June 16-1894 March 9 (Box-folder 6:14)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence; S's n.d. (Box-folder 6:15)
    - Frank M. Thomas to Collins Denny 1894 January 14-1922 April 11 (Box-folder 6:16)
    - John J. Tigert to Collins Denny 1891 February 19-1914 March 21 (Box-folder 7:1)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence 1890 (Box-folder 7:2)
      re: Action as President of Trinity, [1894?]
    - Annie B. Tucker (Mrs. Lyon Tyler) to Collins Denny 1877 January 22-1879 February 5 (Box-folder 7:3)
    - Cassie Tucker to Collins Denny 1872 June 22-1872 July 3 (Box-folder 7:4)
    - George T. Tyler to Collins Denny 1899 April 20-1914 April 16 (Box-folder 7:5)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence 1880-1890 (Box-folder 7:6)
      re: Chaplaincy of University of Virginia, 1888-1899
    - John I. Vance to Collins Denny 1895 May 24-1900 February 15 (Box-folder 7:7)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence 1872-1899 (Box-folder 7:8)
      re: Professorship at Vanderbilt, 1890
    - P. H. Whisner to Collins Denny 1888 June 7-1905 May 6 15 (Box-folder 7:9)
    - Bishop A. W. Wilson to Collins Denny 1896 July 21-1910 August 15 (Box-folder 7:10)
    - A. W. Wilson to Collins Denny 1911 May 22-1916 June 22 (Box-folder 7:11)
    - Nina Wilson to Collins Denny 1889 July 10-1932 Kime 2 (Box-folder 7:12)
    - Dudley G. Wooren to Collins Denny 1875 July 19-1913 February 5 (Box-folder 7:13)
    - Collins Denny Correspondence; W's 1872-1899 (Box-folder 7:14)
    - Collins Denny Miscellaneous Correspondence 1875-1898 (Box-folder 7:15)
    - Collins Denny Sr. Correspondence; W's n.d. (Box 7:16)
  - 1900-1910
    - W. A. Ainsworth to Collins Denny 1909 July 8-1940 September 12 (Box-folder 8:1)
    - E. A. Alderman to Collins Denny 1904 June 20-1918 January 25 (Box-folder 8:2)
    - J. E. Alexander to Collins Denny 1905 May 19-1921 September 17 (Box-folder 8:3)
    - C. M. Anderson to Collins Denny 1904 December. 13-1907 May 7 (Box-folder 8:4)
    - John A. Anderson to Collins Denny 1902 January 24-1932 December 26 (Box-folder 8:5)
    - J. M. Anderson to Collins Denny 1901 February 18-1906 February 1 (Box-folder 8:6)
    - Stonewall Anderson to Collins Denny 1904 February 26-1922 May 29 (Box-folder 8:7)
    - J. R. Andrew to Collins Denny 1905 August 29-1917 June 15 (Box-folder 8:8)
    - J. E. Armstrong to Collins Denny 1901 January 23-1907 February 9 (Box-folder 8:9)